Guide to the Yale University School of Medicine Miscellaneous Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Yale University School of Medicine Miscellaneous Papers.
1810-1886
1863-1885
Ms Coll 4
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
The collection contains papers of the Medical Institution of Yale College (Yale University School of Medicine) including correspondence, committee reports, financial reports, and memorials to the Yale Corporation, especially during the period when Charles A Linsdley served as Dean (1863-1885).
Yale University. School of Medicine
Lindsley, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1826-1906
Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the Medical Historical Library by the Beinecke Library in 1977. Previously the collection had been on long term loan to the Historical Library, since 1961, from the former Rare Book Room at Sterling Memorial Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The first series consists predominantly of incoming correspondence to the Dean of the Medical Institution of Yale College (Yale University School of Medicine), the President of Yale College (Jeremiah Day, Theodore Woolsey, Noah Porter), or the Secretary of Yale College (Franklin B. Dexter). Included are responses to offers of chairs and letters of resignation of chairs. Also, there are a number of letters from graduates of the school who have not yet paid their fees. The second series contains reports of the joint committees of representatives of Yale and the Connecticut Medical Society for nominating professors and for examining candidates for the M.D.; various petitions from students to the medical school; correspondence and memorials from the Dean or medical faculty or committees of the medical faculty to the President and the Yale Corporation; and financial reports of the medical school and requests for appropriations. A number of papers document the medical school's unique relationship with the Connecticut Medical Society and its dissolution in 1879-1884; the school's reorganization as the Medical Department of Yale College in 1879; the School's agreement with the New Haven Dispensary to use its facilities for clinical teaching; and the serious financial problems of the school. Of special note are several early letters related to the organization of the Medical School in 1810-1812, including three letters from Benjamin Silliman to Jonathan Knight (Jr.) in 1812, two letters from Jonathan Knight, Sr. to Jonathan Knight in 1812, and a letter in 1810 from Timothy Gridley to Jonathan Knight, Sr. on recruiting Nathan Smith. The bulk of this collection dates from the deanship of Charles Augustus Lindsley (1863-1885).
Biographical / Historical
The Medical Institution of Yale College was chartered by the Connecticut Legislature in 1810 as a joint project of Yale College and the Connecticut Medical Society. The Society, which had the state's power to set standards and to license candidates for medical practice, agreed to require a year of attendance at Yale or similar medical college in addition to an apprenticeship in order for a candidate to be licensed. Two years attendance were required for an M.D. In return, the representatives of the Society participated jointly with representatives of Yale in nominating professors for vacancies and in examining candidates for the license and the M.D. Leading members of the Medcial Society were invited to address the graduates at the commencement ceremony each year. Also, each county medical society could nominate a student for a free course of lectures for a year. The Medical Institution opened in 1813. with four teaching faculty: Nathan Smith, Benjamin Sillliman, Eli Ives, and Jonathan Knight. Students paid each professor directly for each course. In the period of the deanship of Charles Augustus Lindsley, this system underwent major changes. In 1875, the Medical Institution offered a three year graded course, but because of the agreement with the Connecticut Medical Society, the three years could not yet be required for an M.D. In two stages, 1879 and 1884, the agreement between the Society and Yale was dissolved, ending participation of the Society members on committees and allowing Yale to require the three-year course to obtain an M.D. In 1879, the medical school made an agreement to use the New Haven Dispensary, relocated near the medical school, for clinical teaching. The apprenticeship requirement was replaced by clinical teaching courses at the Dispensary. That same year, the Medical Institution of Yale College became the Medical Department of Yale College and obtained a new charter from the State Legislature. In 1880, students began to pay tuition to Yale College which then paid the professors. In this period, physician/professors made the bulk of their income through private practice. By the 1870s, the Medical School was running at a deficit, and was dependent upon the Corporation to make an annual appropriation from general funds.
Arrangement
Organized in two series: 1. Incoming Letters to the Dean or the Yale Administration. 2. Committees and Internal Records.
Medical colleges -- Connecticut; Medical education -- Connecticut; Bylaws (administrative records); Financial records; Bacon, Francis, 1831-1912; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Dexter, Franklin Bowditch, 1842-1920; Hooker, Worthington, 1806-1867; Hubbard, Stephen G. (Stephen Grosvenor), 1816-1904?; Kingsley, Henry Coit, 1815-1886; Knight, J. (Jonathan), 1789-1864; Lindsley, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1826-1906; Porter, Noah, 1811-1892; Sanford, Leonard J. (Leonard Jacob), 1833-1896; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Smith, David Paige, 1830-1880; Smith, Nathan, 1762-1829; White, Moses Clark, 1819-1900; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Conecticut Medical Society; New Haven Dispensary (New Haven, Conn.); Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution; Yale Corporation; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Incoming Letters to the Dean or the Yale Administration, 1810-1886; Series I
  Arrangement
  Letters by individuals, organized alphabetically, to the Dean of the medical school, the President of Yale (Jeremiah Day, Theodore Woolsey, Noah Porter), or the Secretary of Yale (Franklin B. Dexter). They include, among other subjects, letters of acceptance for positions on the medical faculty and letters of resignation, and letters from former graduates who still owe tuition debt. Some letters are from medical faculty members, expressing their personal opinions to the Yale administration.
  - Incoming Letters A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abernethy, August H., to Worthington Hooker, 1867 October 10
      Scope and Contents
      Late payment of student debt by a graduate (M.D., 1864).
    - Ainey, David C., to Charles A. Lindsley, 1864 June 13
      A former graduate (M.D., 1860) thanks Lindsley for extending the repayment period for student debt.
    - American Medical Association Committee on Medical Education, 1865 May 1
      Dr. Thomas asks, on behalf of the committee, for details of the Medical Institution of Yale College: numbers matriculating and graduating; length of course; presence of summer course; if clinical attendance is required; if dissection is required; and if possession of a diploma alone is sufficient for practice.
    - Asta-Buruaga, Louis, to George Jarvis Brush, 1885 June 27
      Encloses a copy of regulations for examination in medicine in the University of Chile and a copy of Diario Official de la Republica de Chile (November 3, 1884) which recognized the Yale M.D. for practice in Chile. Brush was Professor of Metallurgy at Yale College, 1864-1898.
  - Incoming Letters B (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Baldwin, Simeon E., (Office of) to Lindsley, 1881 June 23
      Legal opinion on the bequest of Dr. David Paige Smith's medical and surgical instruments.
    - Barker, George F., to Noah Porter, 1873 April 9
      Resignation of chair of physiological chemistry and toxicology.
    - Bartow, Samuel B., to [Lindsley], 1869 June 3
      Whether William H. Webster attended and graduated from the medical school.
    - Beard, George M., to Lindsley, 1868 September 30
      Beard (M.D., 1862) sends a bond note for payment of tuition debt.
    - Beckwith, Frank Edwin, to Franklin B. Dexter, 1880 July 3
      Acceptance of the chair of obstetrics.
    - Beckwith, Frank E. to Franklin B. Dexter, 1885 May 2
      Resignation of position.
    - Beers, Timothy P., to Theodore Woolsey, 1855 December 10
      Resignation of chair of obstetrics.
    - Bennett, Hanford N., to Lindsley, 1865 July 17
      Asks if he is on the Committee of Examination. See folder 17.
    - Bentley, Edwin, to Worthington Hooker, 1866 June 22
      On the Bentley Microscopical Prize. See folder 25.
    - Brigham, Norman, to Worthington Hooker, 1865 August 9
      Recommends a student from his county for free tutiton. Each county medical society was allowed to nominate a student from the county for a free set of lectures.
    - Bronson, Henry, to Theodore Woolsey, 1852 January 16
      Resignation of the chair of materia medical and therapeutics.
    - Bronson, S. Henry, to Lindsley, 1879 February 20
      Concerning the New Haven Dispensary. See folder 36.
    - Bronson, S. Henry, to Lindsley, 1879 May 31
    - Brundage, John D., to Lindsley, 1864 July 14
      Brundage (M.D., 1864) inquires about taking the examination for M.D.
    - Burr, Horace, to Lindsley, 1863 December 7
      Despite ill health, he will give the annual address to the graduates.
  - Incoming Letters C (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campbell, James, to Franklin B. Dexter, 1886 July 3
      Acceptance of chair of obstetrics.
    - Carmalt, William H., to Lindsley, 1876 October 13
      Acceptance of lectureship in ophthalmology.
    - Carmalt, William H., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1879 October 30
      Acceptance of chair of ophthalmology.
    - Carrington, Charles, to [Lindsley], 1866 June 11
      Recommendation of Clayton Woodford for a gratuitous course.
    - Coer, Charles F., to Lindsley, 1868 January 4
      Asks for his views on potassium bromide.
    - Connecticut Medical Society to Lindsley, 1866 July 10
    - Connecticut Medical Society to Lindsley, 1883 March 12
      G. W. Chamberlain, Secretary of the Connecticut Medical Society, asks for clarification of the differences between the old and new charters of the Medical Institution of Yale College.
  - Incoming Letters D-G (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - English, James E., to Noah Porter, David P. Smith, and Benjamin Silliman, 1876 April 4
      He is too busy for any new engagements.
    - Fairfield County Medical Society to [Lindsley], 1865 August 16
      Signed by Samuel Sands, Clerk. Recommendation of C. Seymour for a gratuitous course.
    - Fairfield County Medical Society to [Lindsley], 1866 September 28
      Samuel Sands, Clerk. Recommendation of C. T. Morgan for a gratuitous course.
    - Foote, Elial T., to Faculty of the Medical Institution of Yale College, 1864 November 21
      Includes copy of letter from Lindsley to Foote requesting him to sit in the audience at the "Clinique" [Knight Hospital?]. Foote is offended that he cannot sit in the area where other practicing physicians are seated.
    - Gardner, Edwin L., to Lindsley, 1863 December 17
      Gardner (M.D., 1862) asks to defer student debt.
    - Gardner, Edwin L., to Lindsley, 1866 June 8
      Asks to defer student debt.
    - Gridley, Timothy, Hanover, New Hampshire, to Jonathan Knight, Sr., 1810 November 20
      His conversations with Nathan Smith and the possible appointment of Smith to the faculty of the new medical school at Yale.
  - Incoming Letters H (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hamlin, Pra G., to Lindsley, 1870 February 15
      Asks if Lindsley will accept another's bond to pay for tickets to the lectures of Moses White and Dr. Hill. Lindsley redirects the letter to White.
    - Harris, Andrew, to Jeremiah Day, 1838 July 30
      Declines appointment to medical faculty.
    - Hastings, P. M., to Lindsley, 1868 July 14
      Will not be able to attend Examination Committee.
    - Hennepin County Medical Society, Minnesota, to Lindsley, 1869 October 1
      Secretary, W. F. Hutchinson informs Lindsley that H. H. Leonard filed a diploma from Yale dated 1850, but is now practicing homeopathy in this county "with an openly avowed disbelief" in what he was taught. Lindsley might wish to take action. [H. H. Leonard is not listed in published records as a medical graduate of Yale in 1850.]
    - Hill, Asa (President of Connecticut Dental Association), to the President and Faculty of Yale College, 1865 November 2
      Lengthy memorial calling for the establishment of dental instruction at Yale.
    - Hill, Seth, to Lindsley, 1866 September 6
      Former graduate (M.D., 1861) introduces his friend John H. Grannis who wishes to attend medical lectures.
    - Hine, Elmore C., to Lindsley, 1867 March 26
      Former graduate (M.D., 1861) can pay his debt in July or August.
    - Hitchcock, William E., to Lindsley, 1870 Novermber 19
      Former graduate (M.D., 1866) requests a statement of the money he owes.
    - Hubbard, Stephen P., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1879 September 15
      Objects to the appointment of David P. Smith as lecturer in jurisprudence without discussion by the medical faculty.
    - Hubbard, Stephen G., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1879 September 26
      Asks for a meeting to discuss the issue of appointments by the Corporation.
    - Hunt, Ebenezer K. to Lindsley, 1865 February 27
      Asks for a copy of the articles of agreement between Yale College and the Connecticut Medical Society.
    - Hunt, Ebenezer K., to Lindsley, 1865 March 23
      Asks what appropriations, if any, has the city of New Haven made to the Hospital.
    - Hunt, Ebenezer K., to Lindsley, 1867 December 25
      Cannot comply with Lindsley's request (offer of an appointment?)
  - Incoming Letters I-J (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ingersoll, Charles R, (Office of) to Lindsley, 1880 March 24
      Has sent to the Yale Treasurer the amount of the legacy from Mrs. Keese for the benefit of the medical school.
    - Ives, Eli, to Theodore Woolsey, 1853 May 30
      Resignation of the chair of theory and practice of medicine.
    - Ives, Charles Linnaeus, to Noah Porter, 1873 March 7
    - Jackson, James C., Hartford, to Worthington Hooker, 1865 July 5
      The private medical school with which Drs. Leonard Sanford and Francis Bacon are connected [possibly clinical instruction through Knight Hospital] asked permission to print a circular in the Proceedings of the Connecticut Medical Society. Would the Medical School also want a circular printed? A note by Hooker to Lindsley on the back of the letter asks how to respond.
    - Jackson, James C., to Lindsley, 1865 July 13
      Having learned of the pecuniary status of the medical school, he assents to Lindsley's proposition [to request funds from the Connecticut Medical Society or its members?]
  - Incoming Letters K-L (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kenyon, Napoleon B., to Lindsley, 1863 September 4
      Kenyon (M.D., 1864) requests an arrangement for payment for lectures.
    - Knight, Henry M., to Jonathan Knight, 1863 June 16
      Concerning the Medical Society's choice of Leonard Sanford to replace Worthington Hooker, and any misunderstandings that might have occurred.
    - Knight, Henry M., to Lindsley, 1866 July 28
      Received money for expenses for serving on the Examinations Committee.
    - Knight, Jonathan, Sr., Norwalk, to Jonathan Kinght, 1812 March 26
      Written while Jonathan Knight was studying medicine in Philadelphia. Knight became one of the original professors of the Medial Institution of Yale College.
    - Knight, Jonathan, Sr. to Jonathan Knight, 1812 December 9
    - Knight, Jonathan, to Henry M. Knight, 1863 May 30
      Concerniong the nominations made by the Committee on Nomination of Professors.
    - Lewis, George F., to [Lindsley], 1865 August 24
      Sends a check.
  - Incoming Letters M (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Macfarlan, Malcolm, to Lindsley, 1866 October 15
      Macfarlan (M.D., 1865) asks for a certificate attesting to his graduation and Hooker's "testimonial" for a postion in the Army.
    - Mann, Matthew D., to Lindsley, 1879 September 10
      Offers himself as a candidate for lecturer on diseases of women.
    - Mann, Matthew D., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1879 November 17
      Acceptance of lectureship in gynecology.
    - Mann, Matthew D., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1880 October 29
      Will continue as lecturer for another year.
    - Medical and Surgical Reporter to Lindsley, 1863 September 29
      The editor and proprietor, S.W. Butler, requests payment of bill for advertising.
    - Minor, William Chester, to Lindsley, 1867 March 30
      Minor (M.D., 1863) encloses the money still owed for student fees.
    - Morgan, John, to Lindsley, 1868 July 7
      Morgan (M.D., 1869) asks if he can take the examination for M.D.
    - Morgan, John, to Mr. Ingham [?], 1868 August 22
      Will attend the winter course of lecture and asks assistance in finding a place to board with his wife in New Haven.
    - Munson, Byron W., to Lindsley, 1866 August 18
      Munson (M.D., 1869) would like to attend a course of lectures and asks for information.
    - Munson, Byron W., to Lindsley, 1866 August 24
      Thanks him for letter and circular.
    - Munson, Byron W., to Lindsley, 1867 July 8
      About A. J. Steele, who is treating people by medical electricity and whom Munson believes to be a dangerous fraud
  - Incoming Letters N-Q (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Nation to [Lindsley], 1868 August 3
      W .P. Gamson, for the publisher, promotes the benefits to the Medical Institution of advertising in the Nation.
    - New Haven Water Company, 1872 September 26
      Agreement to supply water to the Medical Institution of Yale College for ten years.
    - Paddock, L. S., to Lindsley, 1867 January 29
      Agrees to give the commencement address.
    - Peckham, Fenner H,. to Lindsley, 1863 September 15
      Requests an arrangement for payment of fees for his student N. B. Kenyon (M.D., 1864) and will hold himself responsible.
    - Porter, Issac G., to Lindsley, 1864 November 10
      Concerning giving the commencement address.
    - Porter, Isaac G., to Lindsley, 1865 January 11
      On his coming to New Haven the next day.
    - Porter, Isaac G., to Lindsley, 1865 January 26
      Responds to Lindsleys's request for a copy of his commencement address for publication.
    - Porter, Isaac G. to Lindsley, 1865, February 21
      Sends the corrected proofs.
    - Porter, Isaac G., to Lindsley, 1866 January 16
      Sends a paper containing a notice of the Medical Institution (not included) for possible use by the agent who has been appointed to raise funds.
    - Prudden, T. Mitchell, to Franklin B. Dexter, 1880, July 6
      Reluctantly declines a chair because his present position at the College of Physicians and Surgeons provides better opportunities.
    - Quincy Medical Society to [Lindsley], 1867 August 31
      The Secretary, Addison Niles, who is recording the institution and date of degree for all practitioners in his area, requests a printed list of graduates, or whether Louis Watson graduated from Yale in 1840 [he did].
  - Incoming Letters R (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Rodman, C. S., to Leonard Sanford, 1864 January 12
      Declines a prize of $15 for his [anatomical?] "preparation." The original amount offered was $30.
    - Rowe, Charles H., to Lindsley, 1864 June 14
      Rowe (M.D., 1864) requests Lindsley's recommendation for a position in a military hospital.
    - Rowe, Charles H., to Lindsley, September 1 [no year]
      Requests certification of his graduation and testimony to his "morals."
    - Russell, Gurdon W., to Lindsley, 1865 September 25
      Will give the commencement address.
    - Russell, Gurdon W., to Lindsley, 1866 January 16
      Does not want his address published.
  - Letters: Silliman, Benjamin (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, to Jonathan Knight, 1812 January 4
      These letters relate to the organization of the Medical Institution of Yale College. Silliman, professor of chemistry at Yale, and a future professor of chemistry in the new medical school at Yale, writes to Knight who is studying medicine in Philadelphia. The Prudential committee has appropriated $200 for Knight to bring back anatomical preparations..
    - Silliman, Benjamin, to Jonathan Knight, 1812 January 29
      Discusses the anatomical prepartions desired, including three skeletons. Thinks Kinght has more claim on an appointment in the new school than anyone else.
    - Silliman, Benjamin to Jonathan Knight, 1812 May 18
      Silliman tells Knight that he will be appointed to the faculty and gives him advice on preparation for the position. The appointment is to remain secret for now.
    - Silliman, Benjamin, to Jonathan Knight, 1812 December 22
      Candidacy of Nathan Smith and concern about his "infidelity" in religion.
    - Silliman, Benjamin, to Jeremiah Day, 1838 August 11
      On lectures given by medical faculty for Yale College. Suggests that William Tully be appointed a paid lecturer in botany in Yale College.
  - Letters: Smith, David P. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Smith, David P., to Noah Porter, 1873 March 8
      Expresses his interest in a possible appointment in the medical school.
    - Smith, David P., to Noah Porter, 1873 June 18
      Thanks for appointment as professor of the theory and practice of medicine.
    - Smith, David P., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1873 September 20
      Acceptance of appointment.
    - [Smith] Franklin B. Dexter to David P. Smith, 1878 September 20
      Will discuss with the Corporation authorizing of Smith's suggestion to give lectures on medical jurisprudence.
    - Smith, David P., to Noah Porter, 1878 September 28
      On his lectures on medical jurisprudence.
  - Incoming Letters S-T (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Scofield, W.K., to Lindsley, 1867 December 20
      Former student in 1859-1860 asks about conditions for obtaining a Yale M.D.
    - Shelton, G. A., to Lindsley, 1866 31 July
      Asks for an annual circular of the Medical Institution of Yale College.
    - Silliman, Benjamin (Jr.), to Lindsley, 1879 June 20
      Criticism of Lindsey's memorial to the Corporation that Dispensary physicians and clinical teachers be recognized. The object could be better met through the medical school's plan of reorganization.
    - Smith, Herbert E., to Franklin B. Dexter, 1885 May 26
      Accepts posititon and asks about salary. (Smith becomes professor of chemistry and Dean of the Medical School from 1885 to 1910.)
    - Stearns, H. P., Retreat for the Insane, to Franklin B. Dexter, 1880 October 28
      Agrees to continue for another year as "lecturer on insanity."
    - Thomas, T. Gaillard, to Lindsley, [1879?], October 12
      Recommends Matthew D. Mann for a lectureship. (Mann becomes lecturer in gynecology, 1879-1881.)
    - Tolland County Medical Society to Lindsley, 1866 July 17
      Society recommends Julian N. Parker (M.D., 1867) for a gratuitous course of lectures.
  - Incoming Letters: W-Wh (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Wadsworth, J. W., Austin, Texas, to Lindsley, 1868 December 23
      Would like to attend a course of lectures and requests an annual circular.
    - Wakefield, J. S. to Lindsley, 1869 March 5
      Former student (M.D., 1847) lost his diploma in an Indian outbreak and inquires about obtaining a replacement.
    - Walker, Alfred Eastman, to Lindsley, 1867 June 29